A Guide to the Papers of Charles Brockden Brown, 1769-1922
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Charles Brockden Brown 1769-1922
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6349, etc.
This collections consists of ca. 43 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
6349 and 6349-a were deposited by Clifton Waller Barrett on April 16, 1960, and made gifts on December 30, 1966. 6349-b was a gift of Roger E. Stoddards on November 10, 1972.
Biographical/Historical Information
Charles Brockden Brown was born to a Quaker family in Philadelphia on 17 January 1771. His father was a merchant, descended from a family whose Quaker roots can be traced to the seventeenth century. His maternal ancestors, the Armitts, shared a similar heritage. The family business failed, although Brown's father managed to support his large family, probably through establishing new business activities in real estate.
From about the age of eleven to sixteen, Brown studied under the tutelage of Robert Proud at the Friends Latin School in Philadelphia, and after leaving it he went to work in the Philadelphia law office of Alexander Wilcocks, without having attended college. The legal profession seems to have held little attraction for Brown, but he formed deep friendships at this time, particularly with William Wood Wilkins and Joseph Bringhurst, both of whom shared Brown's literary interests. The three of them were active in the Belles Lettres Club of Philadelphia, which was formed in 1786 and lasted until 1793. When Wilkins, who had gone on to complete his legal education, died in 1795, Brown lost his closest tie to the profession of law. By then Brown had already declined to complete his own education as a lawyer, and the reason for this decision implies much about him as a writer.
Brown had begun experimenting with the writing of literature even while he studied law. In 1789 a handful of his essays, "The Rhapsodist," were published in Columbian Magazine in Philadelphia, and, after abandoning the law a few years later, he dabbled in poetry and fiction. In 1797 he finished a novel called "Sky-Walk." Although he never published it and the manuscript has been lost, parts of it appeared in Edgar Huntly. However, in 1798, he began having his work published at a remarkable pace. During this year, he brought out a portion of Arthur Mervyn, which appeared in the Weekly Magazine (Philadelphia), as well as two complete works, Wieland and Alcuin.
In 1801 Brown had two more novels published, Clara Howard and Jane Talbot. Relative to his previous novels, both these works are less imaginative in their plot structures, and both rely more heavily on the epistolary form. Additionally, neither one employs the kind of bizarre devices, such as ventriloquism or sleepwalking, that Brown had used heavily in earlier fiction.
From 1803 to 1805 Brown also published serially in the Literary Magazine "Memoirs of Carwin the Biloquist." The textual history of this uncompleted story is complex, but apparently the bulk of it was written in 1798 while Wieland was in the process of publication. With additional segments probably written when Brown needed material for the Literary Magazine, the text of "Memoirs of Carwin the Biloquist" appeared during 1803 through March 1805.
The year 1803 saw Brown expending his energies in writings other than fiction. In addition to beginning his association with the Literary Magazine and American Register, Brown departed from Quaker pacifism to write a pamphlet urging the taking of the Louisiana territory, by force if necessary, and opposing Jefferson's policies, which led to the territory's purchase. Brown seems to have achieved popularity in the writing of pamphlets that eluded him as a novelist. His work An Address to the Government of the United States, on the Cession of Louisiana to the French was quickly reprinted, although in a shortened version. Soon after, Brown published a second pamphlet, which like the first attacked Jefferson's policies toward the Louisiana territory.
Toward the end of 1807, Brown introduced a new periodical to replace the Literary Magazine. The journal was entitled the American Register, or General Repository of History, Politics, and Science, and Brown edited five volumes. Although the pages of this journal included literary topics, such as poetry (including Brown's own) and reviews of British and American literature, the main emphasis now reflected Brown's political and historical interests. Essentially, the Register was what its name implied. It kept a record of laws and state papers, but it also gave written accounts of contemporary events, such as a report on the duel between Hamilton and Burr. If most of Brown's remaining literary efforts were devoted to the publication of this journal and the writing of his "Geography," he still had time for one more political pamphlet, a document published in 1809, entitled An Address to the Congress of the United States, on the Utility and Justice of Restrictions upon Foreign Commerce. This publication reflects Brown's continuing interest in public affairs as his career moved toward its end. Once more, his political position placed him in confrontation with Jefferson, this time on the issue of the embargo that had been placed in an attempt to deal with the war then in progress between England and France. Brown, as did many people with mercantile interests, adamantly opposed the embargo.
Brown died in 1810 and was buried in Philadelphia, in the Friends Burial Ground.
Scope and Content
The collection consists chiefly of research material assembled by Daniel E. Kennedy for his projected biography of Brown. These include his commentary on William Dunlap's "Life of Charles Brockden Brown" and miscellaneous notes and annotations on Brown; manuscript copies of other material related to Brown particularly a copy of an article from "Littell's Living Age," 1844, and a copy of Brown's death notice; and a resolution by the Friends of Philadelphia concerning Brown's expulsion for marriage to a non-member by a "hireling minister."
The collection also contains three letters from Brown to William Wood Wilkins and one letter from Wilkins about their friendship, 1790-1793, and a letter to his brother James Brown about Wilkins's death, 1795; a postscript on a 1798 letter from Maria Templeton to Maria NIcholson mentioning yellow fever in Philadelphia; letters to lawyers William P. Beers and John Elihu Hall on literary matters, 1800, 1806; a letter to Mary Linn urging her to cultivate her mind, 1802; and a letter to John B. Romeyn on family matters after the death of his father-in-law, 1808.
In addition there are four letters to his widow Elizabeth, 1812 and n.d. from her brother-in-law William Keese on a financial matter, her son William Linn Brown on a trip to England and a friend Eliza Kane on social matters.
Miscellaneous papers include diplomas of John Blair Linn, 1795-1897 and William Linn Brown, 1821; a bond signed by Elizabeth Linn Brown, 1810; inventories and appraisals of the estates of Charles Brockden Brown, 1810, and Elihu Hubbard Smith, 1799; three receipts to Charles Brockden Brown and Charles Brockden Brown, Jr., 1806, 1821, 1830; the will of Elizabeth Armitt, 1798; a passport of William Linn Brown signed by James Buchanan, 1846; a newsclipping regarding William Linn Brown, 1846; and photographs of the [tombstone?] of Charles Brockden Brown.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into three series: Series I: Literary Manuscripts; Series II: Correspondence; and Series III: Miscellaneous Papers of the Brown and Linn Families.
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - Manuscript commentary concerning William Dunlap's Life of Charles Brockden Brown by Daniel E. Kennedy, mounted with pages from Dunlap in a ledger in a scrapbook format, n.d. [20th c], Volume One, pages 1-105, indexed. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Manuscript commentary concerning William Dunlap's Life of Charles Brockden Brown by Daniel E. Kennedy, mounted with pages from Dunlap in a ledger in a scrapbook format, n.d. [20th c], Volume Two, pages 105-390, indexed. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Manuscript volume, "The Verses of Charles Brockden Brown studied in metre" by Daniel Edwards Kennedy, 1922 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Manuscript copy of an article on Charles Brockden Brown from Littell's Living Age, Volume 2, 1844, copied by Daniel E. Kennedy, n.d. [20th c.], 8 pages stapled within home-made covers. (Box-folder 2:1a)
  - Manuscript copy of a review of Memoirs of Charles Brockden Brown, which first appeared in the London Monthly Review October 1822, copied by Daniel E. Kennedy, n.d. [20th c.], 24 pages stapled within home-made covers. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Manuscript Notice of the Death of Charles Brockden Brown of a consumption in Philadelphia, 1810 Feb, 1 page (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Miscellaneous notes about Charles Brockden Brown by D[aniel] E. Kennedy, n.d. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - "Ossian's Address to the Moon" (print version) by Charles Brockden Brown, with annotations by Daniel E. Kennedy, n.d. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Poem "To the Memory of the late Dr. John B. Linn," "by a young lady" of Philadelphia, 1804, AMs, 4 pages. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Resolution by the Friends of Philadelphia (Quakers) concerning the Expulsion of Charles Brockden Brown from their membership because of his marriage to a non-member by a "hireling minister," 1805 Feb 20, AMs, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:8)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - John Ross to Charles Brown, brother of Charles Brockden Brown, 1769 Sep. 19, ALS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:8a)
    He writes concerning business matters between the two men. He also asks Brown to help their friend, Mr. Craig, if possible.
  - Charles Brockden Brown to William Wood Wilkins, [ca. 1790?], ALS, 6 pages. (Box-folder 2:9)
    He declares his pleasure at receiving letters from his friend, and explains that it is much easier for him to express his feelings in a letter than in person, "my pen is the best interpretation of my sentiments." He also says about his friendship with Wilkins, "Of what importance was this name to me eighteen months ago! And now, next to the idea of myself, it occupies, in partnership with that of another person, my whole attention."
  - Charles Brockden Brown to William Wood Wilkins, [1790-1795?], ALS, 3 pages. (Box-folder 2:10)
    He compares and contrasts love and friendship, saying "without a friend I am miserable." Thanks Wilkins for his kind treatment during his visit to him "while on the banks of the Delaware [River]." "I intended to stay but a single day, and to have resided at Woodbury, but when I arrived at that place and found you absent, I could not resist the inclination to see you."
  - Charles Brockden Brown to William Wood Wilkins, [1792-1793?], ALS, 8 pages. (Box-folder 2:11)
    Brown assures his friend that he is much interested in Wilkins activities in Trenton and that he should not apologize for the subject of his letter. Also tells Wilkins that his own father praised his conduct when he last saw him alone and approved of his son.
  - William Wood Wilkins to Charles Brockden Brown, [ante 1795 Feb 15], ALS, 3 pages. (Box-folder 2:12)
    He apologizes for offending Brown's sensibilities, and hopes to spend more time with him in pleasant companionship.
  - Charles Brockden Brown to his brother, James Brown, 1795 Apr 19, ALS, 2 pages. (Box-folder 2:13)
    Brown writes to his brother in Edenton, North Carolina, about their brother Joseph leaving them, the death of his friend, William Wood Wilkins, and its effect upon his chances in the legal profession, "It is his death that hath prevented me from fulfilling your expectations and obliged me to defer my admission till the succeeding term."
  - Postscript by Charles Brockden Brown on the second page of a letter from Maria Templeton to Maria Nicholson, while in [New York?], 1798 [Aug?], ALS, 2 pages. (Box-folder 2:14)
    He promises to send the entire work of Wieland to her in a few days and says that yellow fever has so far stayed away from Pine Street, although he has lost two friends, Drs. Sayer and Cooper, in Philadelphia.
  - Charles Brockden Brown to William P. Beers, a lawyer of Albany, New York, 1800 Feb 12, ALS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:15)
    He asks Beers to examine a paper that he is sending him and hopes that he will find it worthy of his subscription and thanks him for the copy of one of his speeches.
  - Charles Brockden Brown to Mary Linn, sister of his future wife, 1802 Jan 9, ALS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:16)
    Sends a little volume for her to write in and urges her to cultivate her mind by reading and reflection.
  - Charles Brockden Brown to John E[lihu] Hall, a lawyer of [Baltimore?], including an original poem by Brown, 1806 Nov 21, ALS, 3 pages. (Box-folder 2:17)
    Brown discusses the use of the word Adversaria which was the title of Hall's contributions to his publication, Literary Magazine and American Register, and discusses his plans for a new semi-annual literary magazine, a change made at the suggestion of his publisher, C. and A. Conrad, Philadelphia. He urges his friend to marry and includes a poem as part of his letter about marriage for Hall's benefit.
  - Charles Brockden Brown to John B. Romeyn, 1808 Jan 18, ALS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:18)
    He discusses the impact of the death of his father-in-law, William Linn, upon the unmarried younger members of his family. He was especially concerned about Linn's son, William, who was to be educated for the pulpit. Brown asks for advice from Romeyn about whether William Linn might be interested in the mercantile life and requests any help he could render in finding a place for him with some respected merchant in Albany.
  - William Keese to his sister-in-law, Elizabeth L. Brown, 1812 Feb 19, ALS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:19)
    He encloses a draft for $100.00 as the last quarter's allowance for Henry and mentions a remittance of $75.00 which he sent last week. He asks that Mary acknowledge the receipt of the two sums when she writes to him.
  - James Ogilvie, Savannah, Georgia, to Tart Esquires, possibly a law firm, Charleston, South Carolina, [1813] Apr 23, ALS, 4 pages. (Box-folder 2:19a)
    Ogilvie spends the first half of the letter disputing the claims of a Mr. Johnson to the status of "permanent celebrity" and the second half discussing the possibility of writing the memoirs of Charles Brockden Brown. He asks that they try to procure subscriptions for a Brown biography in Charleston.
  - William Linn Brown, Capes of Delaware, to his mother, Elizabeth L. Brown, n.d., ALS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:20)
    William writes that all is confusion on the vessel and will be until they are cleanly out to sea at daylight. Warns her that she will not likely hear from him until they arrive at Liverpool and mentions his Uncle James [Brown?] in England.
  - Eliza Kane to Mrs. Brown and Miss Linn, n.d., ANS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:21)
    Inviting them to tea.
  - Mr. Kane to Miss Linn, n.d., AN, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:22)
    Inviting her for a ride.
- Series III: Miscellaneous Papers of the Brown and Linn Families
  - Bond signed by Elizabeth Linn Brown, Elijah Brown, Armitt Brown, and James Robertson, 1810 Apr 10 (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Calligraphic samples done by Charles Brockden Brown, Jr. as a boy, 18[?] Jun 6, n.d.
  - Certificate of Membership issued to William Linn Brown, son of Charles Brockden Brown, 1832 Feb 6 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - Diploma of John Blair Linn from Columbia College, 1795 May 16.
  - Diploma of John Blair Linn from Concordia College, 1797 May 13.
  - Diploma of William Linn Brown from Nazareth Hall, 1821 Jun 6 (Box-folder 2:25)
  - Inventory and Appraisement of the Personal Estate of Charles Brockden Brown, late of the City of Philadelphia, 1810 May 19.
  - Additional Inventory of the Estate of Charles Brockden Brown, 1810 Jun 6, ADS, 1 page. (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Inventory of the Estate of Dr. Elihu Hubbard Smith, Physician of New York City, 1799 Jun 1 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - News clipping announcing that William Linn Brown of Pennsylvania was admitted to practice before the U.S. Supreme Court, 1841 Jan 23 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Passport of William Linn Brown, signed by James Buchanan, 1846 Apr 26.
  - Photographs of the Tombstone or Memorial Stone of Charles Brockden Brown and Unidentified Building, with negatives, n.d. (Box-folder 2:29)
  - Receipt for Charles Brockden Brown's Subscription to Dr. Ree's New Cyclopedia, 1806 Nov 11 (Box-folder 2:30)
  - Receipts issued to Charles Brockden Brown, Jr. from the Library Company of Philadelphia for payment of his dues 1821, 1830 (Box-folder 2:31)
  - Will of Elizabeth Armitt, grandmother of Charles Brockden Brown, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1798 May 16, ADS, 3 pages. (Box-folder 2:32)